Miranda Wang: We're here to talk about accidents.
نحن هنا لنتكلم عن الحوادث
How do you feel about accidents?
كيف تشعرون حيال الحوادث؟
When we think about accidents,
عندما نفكر في الحوادث
we usually consider them to be harmful,
عادة ننظر إليها على أنها مؤذية
unfortunate or even dangerous, and they certainly can be.
مشؤومة أو حتى خطرة , ويمكن أن تكون كذلك
But are they always that bad?
لكن هل هي دائما بهذا السوء؟
The discovery that had led to penicillin, for example,
الإكتشاف الذي قاد إلى البنسلين مثلا
is one of the most fortunate accidents of all time.
هو واحد من أكثر الحوادث السعيدة على مر الأوقات.
Without biologist Alexander Fleming's moldy accident,
بدون حادث التعفن لعالم الأحياء ألكسندر فلمينغ
caused by a neglected workstation,
بسبب إهمال في محطة العمل
we wouldn't be able to fight off so many bacterial infections.
لم يكن بمقدورنا محاربة العديد من التعفنات البكتيرية
Jeanny Yao: Miranda and I are here today
جياني ياو: انا وميراندا هنا اليوم
because we'd like to share how our accidents
لأننا نريد أن نشارككم كيف أن حوادتنا
have led to discoveries.
قادنتا إلى إكتشافات
In 2011, we visited the Vancouver Waste Transfer Station
في 2011 , زرنا محطة فانكوفرلنقل النفايات
and saw an enormous pit of plastic waste.
ورأينا حفرة هائلة من النفايات البلاستكية
We realized that when plastics get to the dump,
لاحظنا أنه عندما يحصل تفريغ المواد البلاستيكية
it's difficult to sort them because they have similar densities,
من الصعب فرزها لأن لها كثافة مثشابهة
and when they're mixed with organic matter
وعندما تختلط مع مواد عضوية
and construction debris, it's truly impossible
و مخلفات البناء,فإنه حقا من المستحيل
to pick them out and environmentally eliminate them.
أن تنقل خارجا و يتم القضاء عليها.
MW: However, plastics are useful
ميراندا:مع ذلك,المواد البلاستيكية مفيدة
because they're durable, flexible,
لأنها متينة ومرنة
and can be easily molded into so many useful shapes.
ويمكن بسهولة أن تشكل العديد من الأشكال المفيدة.
The downside of this convenience
الجانب السلبي من هده المقاربة
is that there's a high cost to this.
وهو أن لها تكلفة عالية.
Plastics cause serious problems, such as
البلاستيك يتسبب في مشاكل خطيرة, مثل
the destruction of ecosystems,
تدمير النظم الإيكولوجية,
the pollution of natural resources,
ثلويت الموارد الطبيعية,
and the reduction of available land space.
والتخفيض من مساحة الأراضي المتاحة.
This picture you see here is the Great Pacific Gyre.
الصورة التي ترونها للمحيط الهادي
When you think about plastic pollution
عندما تفكرون في الثلوت البلاستيكي
and the marine environment,
والبيئة البحرية,
we think about the Great Pacific Gyre,
نفكر في المحيط الهادي
which is supposed to be a floating island of plastic waste.
الذي من المفترض أن يكون جزيرة عائمة من النفايات البلاستيكية
But that's no longer an accurate depiction
ولكن هذا لم يعد توصيفا دقيقا
of plastic pollution in the marine environment.
للثلوت البلاستيكي في البيئة البحرية.
Right now, the ocean is actually a soup of plastic debris,
حاليا,المحيط في الواقع حساء من المخلفات البلاستيكية,
and there's nowhere you can go in the ocean
ولا يوجد مكان تدهبون فيه إلى المحيط
where you wouldn't be able to find plastic particles.
حيت لا يمكن أن تجدو فيه أجزاء بلاستيكية.
JY: In a plastic-dependent society,
ج ي : في المجتمعات المعتمدة على البلاستيك
cutting down production is a good goal, but it's not enough.
خفض الإنتاج هدف جيد,لكن ليس كافيا.
And what about the waste that's already been produced?
ومادا عن النفايات التي قد تم إنتاجها ؟
Plastics take hundreds to thousands of years to biodegrade.
البلاستيك يحتاج من مئات إلى الالآف السنينن ليتحلل
So we thought, you know what?
إدن فكرنا, هل تعلمون؟
Instead of waiting for that garbage to sit there and pile up,
بدلا من إنتظار تجمع القمامة وتراكمها
let's find a way to break them down
فلنجد طريقة لتحللها
with bacteria.
مع البكتيريا.
Sounds cool, right?
يبدو هذا رائعا,أليس كدلك ؟
Audience: Yeah. JY: Thank you.
جمهور(نعم),ج.ي: شكرا
But we had a problem.
لكن كانت عندنا مشكلة.
You see, plastics have very complex structures
ترون أن البلاستيك لديها بنيات معقدة
and are difficult to biodegrade.
ومن الصعب أن تتحلل
Anyhow, we were curious and hopeful
مع ذلك, كنا فضوليين ومتفائليين
and still wanted to give it a go.
وأردنا أن نقوم بمحاولة.
MW: With this idea in mind, Jeanny and I read through
م.و: مع هذه الفكرة في الإعتبار , أنا وجياني تصفحنا
some hundreds of scientific articles on the Internet,
بعض مئات المواضيع العلمية على الأنترنيت
and we drafted a research proposal
وأعددنا مقترح بحث علمي
in the beginning of our grade 12 year.
في بداية صفنا الدراسي.
We aimed to find bacteria from our local Fraser River
وحاولنا إيجاد بكتيريا في نهر فريزر المحلي
that can degrade a harmful plasticizer called phthalates.
التي تمكن من تحلل ملدنات ضارة تسمى الفثالات
Phthalates are additives used in everyday plastic products
الفثالات هي المضافات المستخدمة في المنتجات البلاستيكية اليومية
to increase their flexibility, durability and transparency.
لزيادة قدرتها على المرونة والمتانة والشفافية.
Although they're part of the plastic,
على الرغم من انهم جزء من البلاستيك،
they're not covalently bonded to the plastic backbone.
فإنهم لا يشكلون العمود الفقري للبلاستيك.
As a result, they easily escape into our environment.
ونتيجة لذلك,يسهل تسربها إلى بيئتنا
Not only do phthalates pollute our environment,
لا تقوم الفثالات بتلويت بيئتنا فقط
but they also pollute our bodies.
لكن تلوث أجسامنا أيضا.
To make the matter worse, phthalates are found in products
لجعل المسألة أكثر سوءا, الفثالات موجودة في المنتجات
to which we have a high exposure, such as babies' toys,
التي عليها طلب كبير, مثل دمى الأطفال
beverage containers, cosmetics, and even food wraps.
حاويات المشروبات,مستحضرات التجميل,حتى أغلفة الطعام.
Phthalates are horrible because
الفثالات خطيرة لأنها
they're so easily taken into our bodies.
تتسرب بسهولة لأجسامنا.
They can be absorbed by skin contact, ingested, and inhaled.
يمكن أن تمتص عن طريف لمسها الجلد أو بلعها أو إستنشاقها
JY: Every year, at least 470 million pounds of phthalates
ج.ي: كل سنة,هناك 470 مليون من الفثالات
contaminate our air, water and soil.
تفسد الهواء والماء والتربة.
The Environmental Protection Agency
وكالة حماية البيئة
even classified this group as a top-priority pollutant
صنفت هذه المجموعة ضمن الملوثات ذات الأولوية القصوى
because it's been shown to cause cancer and birth defects
لأنه ثبت أنها تتسبب في السرطان والعيوب الخلقية
by acting as a hormone disruptor.
لعملهاكمخل هرموني.
We read that each year, the Vancouver municipal government
قرأنا أنه في كل سنة, حكومة بلدية فانكوفر
monitors phthalate concentration levels in rivers
ترصد مستويات الفتالات في الأنهار
to assess their safety.
لتقييم سلامتها.
So we figured, if there are places along our Fraser River
إذن لاحظنا أنه إذا كانت لدينا أماكن على طول نهر فريزر
that are contaminated with phthalates,
تلوتت بواسطة الفتالات
and if there are bacteria that are able to live in these areas,
وإذا كانت هنا بكتيريا قادر على العيش في هذه المناطق
then perhaps, perhaps these bacteria could have evolved
حينها من الممكن لهذه البكتيريا ان تتطور
to break down phthalates.
لتسحق الفثالات.
MW: So we presented this good idea
إذن قدمنا هده الفكرة الجيدة
to Dr. Lindsay Eltis at the University of British Columbia,
ل د.ليندزي إلتيس في جامعة كولومبيا البريطانية
and surprisingly, he actually took us into his lab
والمدهش, أنه في الواقع أخدنا لمختبره
and asked his graduate students Adam and James to help us.
وطلب من طلابه المتخرجين آدم وجيمس مساعدتنا
Little did we know at that time
ولم نكن نعرف في ذلك الوقت
that a trip to the dump and some research on the Internet
أنها رحلة إلى مزبلة وبعض البحوث على الأنترنيت
and plucking up the courage to act upon inspiration
والتشجع والإلهام
would take us on a life-changing journey
سيأخدنا في ايام متغيرة
of accidents and discoveries.
من الحوادث والإكتشافات
JY: The first step in our project
ج.ي: الخطوة ألأولى في مشروعنا
was to collect soil samples from three different sites
كانت جمع عينات تربة من ثلات مواقع مختلفة
along the Fraser River.
على طول نهر فريزر
Out of thousands of bacteria, we wanted to find ones
بعيدا عن المئات من البكتيريا, كنا نبحت عن واحدة
that could break down phthalates,
تستطيع سحق الفتالات
so we enriched our cultures with phthalates
إذن فقد أغنينا زراعاتنا بالفثالات
as the only carbon source.
كمصدر وحيد للكربون
This implied that, if anything grew in our cultures,
هذا يعني أنه، إذا كان أي شيء ينمو في زراعاتنا ،
then they must be able to live off of phthalates.
عندها يجب أن يكون قادر على العيش خارج الفثالات
Everything went well from there,
كل شيء سار على ما يرام من هناك،
and we became amazing scientists. (Laughter)
وأصبحنا عالمتين مدهشتين
MW: Um... uh, Jeanny. JY: I'm just joking.
م.م: إمم .... جياني. جي:أنا أمزح فقط
MW: Okay. Well, it was partially my fault.
م.و: حسنا. لقد كانت غلطتي
You see, I accidentally cracked the flask
ترون, لقد كسرت عن طريق الخطأ الزجاجة
that had contained our third enrichment culture,
التي كانت تحتوي على زراعتنا المخصبة التالثة,
and as a result, we had to wipe down the incubator room
لذلك كان علينا تنظيف غرفة الحاضنة
with bleach and ethanol twice.
باالأيتانول والمبيض معا
And this is only one of the examples of the many accidents
وهده فقط جزء من مجمل الحوادت
that happened during our experimentation.
التي وقعت لنا أثناء التجارب
But this mistake turned out to be rather serendipitous.
ولكن هذا الخطأ تبين أنه سار عكس المتوقع
We noticed that the unharmed cultures
فقد لاحظنا أن العينات السليمة
came from places of opposite contamination levels,
جاءت من أماكن لمستويات التلوث النقيضة،
so this mistake actually led us to think that
وهذا الخطأ أدى بنا إلى الاعتقاد بأنه
perhaps we can compare
ربما يمكننا مقارنة
the different degradative potentials of bacteria
اختلاف إمكانيات الهدم للبكتيريا
from sites of opposite contamination levels.
حسب مواقع مستويات التلوث المناقضة لها.
JY: Now that we grew the bacteria,
JY: الآن بعد أن كبرنا البكتيريا،
we wanted to isolate strains by streaking onto mediate plates,
أردنا عزل سلالات وذلك بلطخها على صفائح متوسطة
because we thought that would be
لأننا كنا نظن أنها ستكون
less accident-prone, but we were wrong again.
أقل عرضة للحوادث، ولكن كنا على خطأ مرة أخرى.
We poked holes in our agar while streaking
أحدثنا ثقوب على الأغرة ريثما نلطخها
and contaminated some samples and funghi.
ولوثنا بعض العينات والفونغي.
As a result, we had to streak and restreak several times.
كنتيجة لذلك، كان علينا أن لطخها ولطخها عدة مرات.
Then we monitored phthalate utilization
عندها رصدنا فعالية الفثالات
and bacterial growth,
والنمو البكتيري،
and found that they shared an inverse correlation,
ووجد أنهما يشتركان في علاقة عكسية،
so as bacterial populations increased,
عند زيادة البكتيريا الملوثة
phthalate concentrations decreased.
تنخفض تركيزات الفثالات.
This means that our bacteria were actually living off of phthalates.
وهذا يعني أن البكتيريا كانت فعلا تعيش خارج الفثالات.
MW: So now that we found bacteria that could break down phthalates,
م و: حتى الآن عثرنا على البكتيريا التي يمكن أن تدمرالفثالات
we wondered what these bacteria were.
كنا نتساءل ما هذه البكتيريا.
So Jeanny and I took three of our most efficient strains
إذن أنا وجيني أخدنا ثلات أكثر سلالات فعالة لدينا
and then performed gene amplification sequencing on them
ونفدنا تضخم جيني متسلسل عليها
and matched our data with an online comprehensive database.
وطابقنا بياناتنا مع قاعدة بيانات شاملة على إنترنت.
We were happy to see that,
كنا سعداء أن نرى أنه،
although our three strains had been previously identified bacteria,
على الرغم من أن كان لدينا ثلاث سلالات من البكتيريا التي سبق تحديدها،
two of them were not previously associated
اثنان منهم لم تكن سابقا مرتبطة
with phthalate degradation, so this was actually a novel discovery.
مع تناقص الفثالات، لذا كان هذا اكتشاف جديدا فعلا.
JY: To better understand how this biodegradation works,
JY: لنفهم على نحو أفضل كيف يعمل هذا التحلل الأحيائي،
we wanted to verify the catabolic pathways of our three strains.
كنا نريد التحقق من مسارثلاث سلالات لدينا.
To do this, we extracted enzymes from our bacteria
للقيام بهذا، استخرجنا الأنزيمات من البكتيريا لدينا
and reacted with an intermediate of phthalic acid.
وفاعلناها مع متوسط لحمض فثاليك.
MW: We monitored this experiment with spectrophotometry
م و: رصدنا هده التجربة بواسطة قياس الضوء الطيفي
and obtained this beautiful graph.
وحصلت على هذا الرسم البياني الجميل.
This graph shows that our bacteria really do have
يوضح هذا الرسم البياني أن البكتيريا لها
a genetic pathway to biodegrade phthalates.
طريقة وراثية لتحلل إحيائياً الفثالات.
Our bacteria can transform phthalates, which is a harmful toxin,
البكتيريا يمكن أن تحول الفتالات التي هي عبارة عن مادة سامة
into end products such as carbon dioxide, water
إلى منتجات نهائية مثل ثاني أكسيد الكربون، الماء
and alcohol.
والكحول.
I know some of you in the crowd are thinking,
وأنا أعلم أن البعض منكم في الحشد يتساءلون,
But if our bacteria did not evolve to break down phthalates,
ولكن إذا لم تتطور لدينا البكتيريا لسحق الفتالات
they would have used some other kind of carbon source,
عندها سيتكون لدينا مصدر جديد للكربون
and aerobic respiration would have led it
و التنفس الهوائي سيؤدي
to have end products such as carbon dioxide anyway.
إلى وجود المنتجات النهائية مثل ثاني أكسيد الكربون على أي حال.
We were also interested to see that,
كنا أيضا مهتمات لمعرفة ذلك،
although we've obtained greater diversity
على الرغم أنه حصلنا على قدر أكبر من التنوع
of bacteria biodegraders from the bird habitat site,
من البكتيريا المتحللة من مساكن الطيور،
we obtained the most efficient degraders from the landfill site.
حصلنا علي أكثر الملوثات فعالية من موقع دفن النفايات.
So this fully shows that nature evolves
وبالتالي هذا يظهر تماما أن الطبيعة تتطور
through natural selection.
عن طريق الانتقاء الطبيعي.
JY: So Miranda and I shared this research
JY: أنا وميرندا ، شاركنا بهده البحوث
at the Sanofi BioGENEius Challenge competition and were recognized
في منافسات تحدي سانوفي بيوجينيوس وتم الإعتراف بها
with the greatest commercialization potential.
مع إمكانية تسويق كبرى.
Although we're not the first ones to find bacteria
على الرغم من أننا لسنا أول من عثر على البكتيريا
that can break down phthalates,
التي يمكن أن تسحق الفثالات
we were the first ones to look into our local river
كنا أول من بحث في نهرنا المحلي
and find a possible solution to a local problem.
و وجدنا حل ممكن لمشكلة محلية.
We have not only shown that bacteria
ونحن لم نظهر فقط أن البكتيريا
can be the solution to plastic pollution, but also that
يمكن أن تكون حلاً لتلوث البلاستيك، ولكن أيضا أن
being open to uncertain outcomes and taking risks
تكون منفتحا على نتائج غير أكيدة وأن تخاطر
create opportunities for unexpected discoveries.
تخلق فرص لاكتشافات غير متوقعة.
Throughout this journey, we have also discovered our passion for science,
طوال هذه الرحلة، اكتشفنا أيضا أن لنا حماساً للعلوم
and are currently continuing research
ونواصل حاليا البحث
on other fossil fuel chemicals in university.
على مواد الوقود الأحفوري الكيميائية في الجامعة.
We hope that in the near future,
التي نأمل في المستقبل القريب،
we'll be able to create model organisms
أن تكون قادرة على خلق نموذج للكائنات الحية
that can break down not only phthalates
التي يمكن أن تسحق ليس فقط الفثالات
but a wide variety of different contaminants.
لكن مجموعة متنوعة واسعة من الملوثات المختلفة.
We can apply this to wastewater treatment plants
يمكن أن نطبق هذا على محطات معالجة مياه الصرف الصحي
to clean up our rivers
لتنظيف الأنهار
and other natural resources.
وغيرها من الموارد الطبيعية.
And perhaps one day we'll be able to tackle
وربما يوم ما سوف نكون قادرين على معالجة
the problem of solid plastic waste.
مشكلة النفايات البلاستيكية الصلبة.
MW: I think our journey has truly transformed
مي و : أعتقد أن رحلتنا قد حولت حقاً
our view of microorganisms,
نظرتنا للكائنات الحية الدقيقة،
and Jeanny and I have shown that
وجيني وأنا ،أظهرنا أنه
even mistakes can lead to discoveries.
يمكن أن تؤدي الأخطاء للاكتشافات.
Einstein once said,
قال اينشتاين ذات مرة،
"You can't solve problems by using the same kind
"لا يمكنك حل المشاكل باستخدام نفس النوع
of thinking you used when you created them."
من التفكير الذي استخدمته عند خلقك لها "
If we're making plastic synthetically, then we think
إذا كنا ننتج البلاستيك صناعيا، عندها نفكر
the solution would be to break them down biochemically.
أنه سيكون الحل القضاء عليها كيميائيا.
Thank you. JY: Thank you.
شكرا. JY: شكرا لك.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)